Guide to the William G. Butler Photography Collection 1875-2015 PR 425
New-York Historical Society
William G. Butler photography collection
1875-2015
New-York Historical Society
Butler, William G., 1945-2020
PR 425
2 Linear feet in five boxes and one flat folder.
The William G. Butler photography collection, collected by William G. Butler, consists primarily of photographs of New York City from 1890-2015. The earliest document in the collection, from 1875, is a page from an Ulster County atlas.
Arrangement
In this collection each item is arranged first by date in chronological order, then by title in alphabetical order. Although oversized photographs are housed separately from the rest of the collection, they are arranged by the previously stated parameters.
Biographical / Historical
This photography collection was created by William G. Butler, art and photography collector. He has also donated part of his collection to the Palm Springs Art Museum, which showed a curation of his donations in a 2019 exhibit "Contemporary Sublime: The Photographic Collecting of William G. Butler".
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact printroom@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift, estate of William G. Butler, 2021.
Scope and Contents
The William G. Butler photography collection consists primarily of vintage photographs of New York City collected by Butler. Many of the photographs were taken for publication and originally owned by newspicture agencies or press associations. The content of the photographs is varied, however many are views of cityscapes or street scenes and city life. The majority of the photographs are silver gelatin prints. While some artists are known, the collection does not consist of a series by any particular artist. Many of the photographs seem to have been titled by a third party rather than the photographer and are bracketed in this finding aid to distinguish them as later additions. The collection also includes a small number of non-photographic pictorial works. The container list includes a complete item level inventory of the collection.
New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Street photography -- New York (State) -- New York.; Cityscapes (representations)
- [County Atlas of Ulster], 1875 (Oversize FF1, Item 99)
  Scope and Contents
  Atlas pages 45 and 46. Page 45: complete map of Olive, New York; Page 46 is one-half of a spread of Ulster County. Authored by F.W. Beers, Superintendant, published by Walker and Jewett.
- [New York City/Coney Island?], 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Item 1)
  Printed later in 1960.
- [Fifth Avenue New York], 1899 (Offsite-box 1, Item 2)
  Printed later in the 1950's. While the photographer is unknown, the photo originates from Ewing Galloway's photography agency.
- [New York, NY], 1905 (Offsite-box 1, Item 3)
  This photograph, printed later, features 161st street between Amsterdam and St. Nicholas Avenues. The picture is stamped and signed on the back, however the name of the artist is unclear.
- [5th Avenue, NYC], 1912 (Offsite-box 1, Item 4)
  Printed in the 1950's. While the photographer is unknown, the photo originates from Ewing Galloway's photography agency.
- [Workers, Brooklyn Bridge], 1914 (Offsite-box 1, Item 5)
  The photographer is Eugene de Salignac. It appears to have been taken for or in the possession of the New York Post, which is stamped on the back.
- [NYC], 1920s (Offsite-box 1, Item 6)
  The photograph seems to have originally been the possession of Air France and published in their "Tele-Magazine" as noted on the back.
- [Nassau Street NYC], 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Item 7)
- [New York City], 1924 (Offsite-box 1, Item 8)
  This photograph, printed later, features two people with street vending boxes hanging from their necks as they warm their hands over a fire.
- [New York], 1924 (Offsite-box 1, Item 9)
  Pictures Nassau Street.
- [Fifth Avenue, NYC], 1925 (Offsite-box 1, Item 10)
- [Fifth Avenue, NYC], 1925 (Offsite-box 1, Item 11)
- [Fire Madame Tussaud's Wax Museum], 1925 (Offsite-box 5, Item 93)
- [Iron Workers, NYC], 1925 (Offsite-box 1, Item 12)
- [Fifth Ave, NYC], 1926 (Offsite-box 1, Item 13)
  Printed later.
- [Broad Street, NYC], 1927 (Offsite-box 1, Item 14)
  While the photographer is unknown, the picture appears to have been in the possession of the New York Evening Post in which it was published (as noted on the back).
- [Coney Island], 1927 (Offsite-box 1, Item 15)
  The photograph is attributed to ACME NEWSPICTURES and includes a caption on the back.
- [Brooklyn Bridge, NYC], 1930s (Offsite-box 1, Item 16)
- [Weehawken Docks, NJ], 1930s (Offsite-box 1, Item 17)
- [Grand Central Terminal, New York], 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Item 18)
- [New York City], 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Item 19)
  Accredited to the New York Post.
- [Swimming Pool, Jones Beach, NY], 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Item 20)
  New York Post photograph.
- [Woolworth Tower, NYC], 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Item 21)
  Associated Press photograph.
- [Times Square, NYC], 1933 (Offsite-box 1, Item 22)
- [Men in Acrobatic Poses at Machinery], 1934 (Oversize FF1, Item 102)
  Photo credit is to General Electric
- [Snow at 47th and Broadway, NYC], 1934 (Offsite-box 2, Item 23)
- [Metropolitan Opera House, NYC], 1935 (Offsite-box 2, Item 24)
  Accredited to the Wide World Studio, caption on the back.
- [Times Square, NYC (Chevy, Planters)], 1937 (Offsite-box 2, Item 25)
  Accredited to ACME NEWSPICTURE.
- [Wall Street, NYC], 1937 (Offsite-box 2, Item 26)
  This photograph features the New York Stock Exchange. Accredited to Keystone View Co.
- [New York, NY], 1939 (Offsite-box 2, Item 27)
- [Central Park (Ice Skaters)], 1940s (Offsite-box 2, Item 28)
- [Times Square], 1940s (Offsite-box 2, Item 29)
- [New York City], 1940 (Offsite-box 2, Item 30)
  This photograph features a crowd gathered outside a crime scene on 138th street. Accredited to ACME NEWSPICTURES.
- [Times Square NYC (above Chevy)], 1940 (Offsite-box 2, Item 31)
  This photograph was taken by Lou Stoumen in 1940 and printed in 1986. It was previously held by the Milwaukee Art Museum and Floyd and Josephine Segel.
- [Central Park NYC], 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Item 32)
- [Coney Island Boardwalk, NYC], 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Item 33)
  Accredited to ACME NEWSPICTURES. Caption on the back.
- [Grand Central Station], 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Item 34)
- [Grand Central Station], 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Item 35)
- [Music Box NYC], 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Item 36)
- [New York, NY], 1941 (Oversize FF1, Item 101)
  This photograph features Central Park.
- [Penn Station], 1941 (Offsite-box 2, Item 37)
- [Times Square], 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Item 38)
- [Times Square], 1942 (Offsite-box 2, Item 39)
- [Times Square], 1943 (Offsite-box 2, Item 40)
- [Brooklyn, NY], 1944 (Offsite-box 2, Item 41)
  This photograph features a crowd of evacuees after a chlorine gas explosion. Accredited to ACME NEWSPICTURE INC.
- [Central Park, NYC (snow)], 1945 (Offsite-box 2, Item 42)
- [Macy's Day Parade], 1945 (Offsite-box 2, Item 43)
- [Moon Over Manhattan, NYC], 1945 (Offsite-box 2, Item 44)
  Taken by Charles Langer at ACME NEWSPICTURE INC.
- [NYC], 1945 (Offsite-box 3, Item 45)
  Taken by David McLane and accredited to ACME NEWSPICTURE INC.
- [NYC (crosstown street in the rain)], 1945 (Offsite-box 3, Item 46)
- [Park Avenue NYC], 1945 (Offsite-box 3, Item 47)
- [Coney Island], 1946 (Offsite-box 3, Item 48)
  Associated Press photo, caption on the back.
- [Grand Central Station], 1946 (Offsite-box 3, Item 49)
- [Times Square], 1946 (Offsite-box 3, Item 50)
- [Coney Island], 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Item 51)
- [Mulberry Street, NYC], 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Item 52)
- [Times Square, NYC], 1947 (Offsite-box 3, Item 53)
- [Times Square, NYC Snow], 1948 (Offsite-box 3, Item 54)
  Associated Press photo.
- [Broadway and 47th, NYC], 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Item 55)
- [Manhattan, NYC (long exposure)], 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Item 56)
- [New York (night traffic, 6th Ave)], 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Item 57)
- [NYC (high above 6th and Broadway)], 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Item 58)
- [NYC (man on payphone, night)], 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Item 59)
- [Ten Nights in a Dance Hall], 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Item 60)
- [New York], 1950s (Offsite-box 3, Item 61)
- [NYC (man in snow)], 1950s (Offsite-box 3, Item 62)
- [Coney Island, NYC], 1951 (Offsite-box 5, Item 91)
- [Times Square], 1951 (Offsite-box 3, Item 63)
- [Bronx], 1952 (Offsite-box 3, Item 64)
  This photograph was featured in an article on Broadway in an unspecified publication.
- [NYC (Peanut Vendor) Downtown], 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Item 65)
  Press photo, caption on the back.
- [Coney Island], 1953; Ferris Wheel (Offsite-box 4, Item 66)
- [Coney Island], 1953 (Offsite-box 4, Item 67)
- [Times Square], 1955 (Offsite-box 4, Item 68)
  Associated Press photograph of a bomb scare in Times Square.
- [Park Avenue, NYC], 1957 (Offsite-box 4, Item 69)
  Press photograph.
- [NYC (Saks)], 1958 (Offsite-box 4, Item 70)
  Press photo.
- [New York, NY], 1960s (Offsite-box 4, Item 71)
  This photograph, taken and printed in the 1960's, pictures the 59th Street Bridge/Ed Koch Queensboro Bridge
- [New York, NY (harbor view)], 1960s (Offsite-box 4, Item 72)
- [Sophia Loren], 1960s (Offsite-box 5, Item 89)
- [Sophia Loren], 1960s (Offsite-box 5, Item 90)
- [Times Square, NYC], 1960 (Offsite-box 4, Item 73)
- [Atop 30 Rockefeller Center, NYC], 1961 (Offsite-box 4, Item 74)
  This photograph features the releasing of balloons by Johnny Maguire and Mariann Kelly for the March of Dimes Campaign.
- [New York City], 1961 (Offsite-box 4, Item 75)
- [Waldorf Astoria Hotel, NYC], 1961 (Offsite-box 4, Item 76)
- [Central Park], 1962 (Offsite-box 4, Item 77)
- [Free Seatbelts], 1962 (Offsite-box 5, Item 94)
  Accredited to United Press International Photo.
- [Chelsea NYC], 1963 (Offsite-box 4, Item 78)
  Pictures Chelsea during a blackout.
- [Brooklyn Bridge], 1965 (Offsite-box 4, Item 79)
- [Central Park] 1965 (Offsite-box 4, Item 80)
- [NYC (Save Water, Goodyear Blimp)], 1965 (Offsite-box 4, Item 81)
- [Sixth Avenue], 1965 (Offsite-box 4, Item 82)
- [Coney Island], 1966 (Offsite-box 4, Item 83)
- [Lower East Side, NY], 1966 (Offsite-box 4, Item 84)
  Pictures Orchard Street.
- [Orchard Street, Lower East Side NY], 1966 (Offsite-box 4, Item 85)
- [Maxwell Street Fur Coats], 1968 (Offsite-box 4, Item 86)
  The photograph, printed later, pictures a street vendor with his merchandise (fur coats). The picture signed on the back by the artist, Ave Pildas.
- [Manhattan (Goldwater Hospital)], 1969 (Offsite-box 4, Item 87)
- [42nd St., NY], 1976 (Oversize FF1, Item 103)
  Photograph by Michael DeChellis, signed on the back. Taken in 1976, this photograph was printed later.
- [World Trade Center, Brooklyn Bridge], 1997 (Oversize FF1, Item 104)
  This photograph by Chris Bliss was taken in 1997 but printed later.
- Bread of Life, 2012 (Oversize FF1, Item 98)
  This photograph features a neon sign from which the title of the photograph is derived. The photograph is printed with archival pigment and signed by the artist John Dubois.
- Piazza San Barnaba, 2014 (Oversize FF1, Item 100)
  This photograph, featuring a cafe, is signed by the artist Jim M Kimmin.
- T.SQ NEWSSTAND, 2015 (Offsite-box 5, Item 95)
  This publication features pictorials of Times Square by various artists over various periods. The material is presented in a magazine-like form.
- [Triborough Bridge], undated (Oversize FF1, Item 97)
  This photograph of Triborough Bridge is signed by the artist Francesca Ifilligi.
- [untitled], undated (Offsite-box 4, Item 88)
  This photograph features an aerial view of the New York skyline. The photograph was taken by Jon Hughes and is accredited as a press photo on the back.
- [untitled], undated (Offsite-box 5, Item 91)
  Contemporary, features urinals and graffiti.
- [untitled], undated (Oversize FF1, Item 105)
  Photograph of NYC skyline.